Guide to the John Ruskin Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Ruskin collection
1826-1949
1840-1885
GEN MSS 1168
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.52
(39 boxes)
Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Acquisition information about specific items has been included in this finding aid after the description of the item as available. For additional information, see the appropriate curator.
Scope and Contents
The John Ruskin Collection contains correspondence, writings, artwork, and other material relating to the life and career of the Victorian author and art critic John Ruskin. Major correspondents include his parents, John James Ruskin and Margaret Cox Ruskin; George Allen; Edward Clayton; William Graham; Henry Jowett; Robert C. Leslie; Frederic Maynard; Susanna Miller; Sir John Naesmyth and Lady Naesmyth; Edward B. Nicholson; William Roscoe Osler; Harriette Rigbye; and Mrs. Arthur Stannard (who published as John Strange Winter). Writings include notebooks of Ruskin's juvenilia and other poems by Ruskin; autograph manuscripts of "The Mysteries of Life and its Arts" and several of his lectures; the manuscript of his autobiography, "Praeterita;" and corrected page proofs of chapters from Modern Painters and page and galley proofs of Sesame and Lilies. Artwork includes fourteen watercolors and pen and ink sketches by Ruskin. The collection also contains photographs of Ruskin; notes taken by Alexander H. M. Wedderburn at Ruskin's 1874 lectures in Oxford; and a leather postbag stamped with Ruskin's name and address.
John Ruskin (1819-1900)
John Ruskin (1819-1900), author, art critic, educator and social theorist of the Victorian period. Ruskin was educated primarily by his parents, John James Ruskin and Margaret Cox Ruskin, and then at Oxford University, where he received his degree in 1842. His multivolume Modern Painters (1843-1860) championed the work of J. M. W. Turner and the use of symbolism in art and was a major influence on the Pre-Raphaelite movement. The Stones of Venice (1851-1853) was an influential appreciation of Gothic art and architecture and a work of implicit social criticism. Other important writings included Unto this Last (1862); the lectures pubished as Sesame and Lilies (1865); and the pamphlet series published as Fors Clavigera (1871-1884).
Ruskin was the first Slade Professor of Fine Art at Oxford University and founded the Ruskin School of Drawing and Fine Art (1871) in Oxford. In the same year, he established the Guild of St. George (1871). He spent his last years in retirement, suffering several mental breakdowns, at Brantwood, a small estate in the Lake District, and died there of influenza on January 20, 1900. Ruskin's only marriage, in 1848, was to Effie Gray Ruskin Millais (1828-1897); it was annulled in July of 1854.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1829-1949; II. Manuscripts, 1826-1897; III. Artwork, 1846-1874; IV. Other Material, 1847-1874.
Artists -- Great Britain; Authors, English -- 19th century; English literature -- 19th century; English poetry -- 19th century; English prose literature -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Allen, George, 1832-1907; Clayton, Edward, 1817-1895; Graham, William, 1839-1911; Jowett, Henry; Leslie, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1826-1901; Maynard, Frederic W.; Miller, Susanna; Naesmyth, John, Sir; Naesmyth, Lady; Nicholson, Edward Williams Byron, 1849-1912; Osler, W. Roscoe (William Roscoe); Rigbye, Harriette; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Ruskin, John James; Ruskin, Margaret Cock, 1781-1871; Winter, John Strange, 1856-1911
- Correspondence, 1829-1949; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, has been arranged into four subseries: Bound Volumes of Correspondence; Letters from John Ruskin to Identified Individuals; Letters to John Ruskin to Unidentified Individuals; and Third Party Correspondence.
  - Bound Volumes of Correspondence
    - 137 autograph letters, signed, mostly to John James Ruskin. Various places. Bound in blue morocco., 1827-1859; (1 volume) (Box 1)
      Bound together with eight early poems, beginning with "Look at that ship," 1827 February or March.
      Other correspondents include: Margaret Cox (Cock) Ruskin, Miss Mitford, J. C. Louden, and W. L. Brown.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Bought at Sotheby's, 1930
    - 152 autograph letters, signed, to John James Ruskin, and 7 autograph letters, signed, to Margaret Cox Ruskin. Various places. Bound in blue morocco., 1845-1850; (1 volume) (Box 1)
      Bound together with 31 autograph letters, signed, from John James Ruskin to John Ruskin; 2 autograph letters, signed, from Margaret Cox Ruskin to John Ruskin; and an autograph letter, signed, from John James Ruskin to Margaret Cox Ruskin. 1831-1852.
    - 304 autograph letters, signed, to John James Ruskin, and 3 autograph letters, signed, to Margaret Cox Ruskin. Various places. In boards and bound in blue morocco., 1851 August-1852 July; (1 volume) (Box 2)
      Bound together with 3 autograph letters, signed, from John Ruskin to the "Times."
    - 120 autograph letters, signed, to John James Ruskin, and 2 autograph letters, signed, to Margaret Cox Ruskin. Scotland. Bound in blue morocco., 1853 June-December; (1 volume) (Box 2)
      Bound together with 3 autograph letters, signed, from John Ruskin to Miss Mitford, [1853?] August 17, 1854 October 3, no date. Also includes one fragment of an autograph letter possibly addressed to Miss Mitford.
      Bound together with an autograph letter, signed, from John James Ruskin to John Ruskin, 1853 July 14.
    - 290 autograph letters, signed, 10 typed copies of letters, and one letter, partly autograph partly typed copy, to John James Ruskin. Switzerland and Italy. Bound in blue morocco., 1857 April-1861 December; (1 volume) (Box 3)
      Bound together with 13 autograph letters, signed, from Margaret Cox Ruskin to John Ruskin, 1864 December-1867 August.
      Bound together with a manuscript copy of a letter to La Comtesse de Montemerli from John Ruskin, 1858 August 8.
    - 434 autograph letters, signed, to John James Ruskin. Various places. Bound in blue morocco., 1862 May-1863 December; (1 volume) (Box 3)
    - 20 manuscript copies of letters in an unidentified hand addressed to various newspapers on such subjects as the Pre-Raphaelites, the Italian question, foreign policies, etc. Bound in three-quarter green morocco with binder's title: "Ruskin's Letters, 1851-1877". (Box 3)
      Gift of Howard S. Mott, 1958
      Custodial History
      Autograph of Richard Herne Shepherd on front pastedown
    - 2 manuscript copies of letters in an unidentified hand to Ruskin's editors. Bound in three-quarter green morocco with binder's title: "Ruskin's Letters"., undated (Box 4)
    - Typescript copies of letters to Dr. John Brown with manuscript notes in the hand of Alexander H. M. Wedderburn and Joan Ruskin (Agnew) Severn (Mrs. Arthur Severn). Bound in blue cloth with binder's title: "Letters from John Ruskin to Dr. John Brown"., 1846-1882 (Box 4)
      Bought on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1937
    - 39 autograph letters, signed, to Robert C. Leslie. Mounted in two brown cloth albums together with various clippings by Ruskin, reviews of Leslie's "A Sea Painter's Log", and a signed photograph of John Brett., 1882-1889; (2 volumes) (Box 4)
      Bought on the Plain Fund, 1954
    - Manuscript and typescript copies of letters to his father and other persons. Manuscript notes and copies in the hand of Alexander H. M. Wedderburn., 1845-1863; (3 volumes) (Box 5)
    - Manuscript and typescript copies of letters to his father and other persons. Manuscript notes and copies in the hand of Alexander H. M. Wedderburn., 1845-1863; (2 volumes) (Box 6)
  - Letters from John Ruskin to Identified Individuals
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Francesca Alexander]. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1886 March 23 (Box 7)
      Accompanied by a typed letter, signed, from Charles E. Goodspeed to James T. Babb concerning the origin of the letter, 1944 April 3
      Gift of Charles E. Goodspeed, 1944
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, to George Allen. Oxford, Brantwood, Herne Hill., [1873?] (Box 7)
      Bought on the Small Fund, 1987 January 20
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, to George Allen. No place and Oxford., [1875?] May and [1876] February 10 (Box 7)
      Bought from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc. by Chauncey Brewster Tinker, 1930
    - Autograph letter, signed, to George Allen. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1877 October 2 (Box 7)
      Bought on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999 April 23
    - 2 autograph letters, signed with initials, to George Allen. Brantwood., 1879 January 11 and 1883 January 8 (Box 7)
      Bought from Winifred A. Myers (Autographs) Ltd. on the Robert H. Taylor Fund, 1953
    - Autograph letter, signed, to George Allen. Ambleside (Coniston)., 1881 May 15 (Box 7)
      Bought on the William Lyon Phelps Memorial Fund, 1956
    - 7 autograph letters, signed, to George Allen. Various places., 1882 (Box 7)
      Bought on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1988 September 13
      With three original envelopes
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [George] Allen. Coniston., 1884 July 9 (Box 7)
      Bought from F. H. Sweet on the Plain Fund, 1941 April
      Accompanied by a copy of the note from a sales catalogue, a portrait of Ruskin, and a program from the memorial service held for John Ruskin at Westminster Abbey, 1900 January 25.
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 4 typed letters (copies) to George Allen., 1874-1884 (Box 7)
      Bought on the Charles J. Rosenbloom Fund, 2003 June 30
    - 7 autograph letters, signed, to George Allen. Various places., 1884-1888 (Box 7)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1952 September 3
    - Autograph letter, signed, to George Allen. Oxford., undated (Box 7)
      Bought on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1958
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Hugh Allen., undated (Box 7)
      Bought from Goodspeed's Bookshop, Inc. on the Charles J. Rosenbloom Fund, 2003 June 30
      Accompanied by a drawing by Allen, with commentary by Ruskin; an envelope, dated 1884 November 4; 2 newspaper clippings; and a photograph of an engraved portrait of Ruskin.
    - 14 autograph letters, signed, to William Allingham. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire, Tunbridge Wells, Denmark Hill, and London. In a red cloth case., 1855-1877, undated (Box 7)
      Includes four envelopes.
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1947
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [J. C.] Armytage., [circa 1843-1844] (Box 7)
      Bought from Roy Davids Ltd. on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998 January 14
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Professor Attwell. Amiens., 1880 October 17 (Box 7)
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1959
      Includes envelope.
    - 6 autograph letters, signed, to George Baker. Coniston, Lancashire, Oxford., 1877 July 18-1885 December 11 (Box 7)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Frank Altschul Fund, 2003 June 30
      Includes 4 envelopes
    - Autograph letter in third person to Mr. Ball. Denmark Hill., 1855 December 12 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 1997 February 27
      Mounted on an album leaf, with "The Late George Dixon, M. P." on verso.
    - 5 autograph letters, signed, to John Barratt. Oxford, Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1878-1879, undated (Box 7)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Library Associates Fund, 1964
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Barrington., 1883 November 20 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999 August 16
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Peter?] Baxter. Canterbury., 1880 October 6 (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Peter Bayne. No place., undated (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Susan [Beever]. No place., undated (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. [Bennoch?]. No place., [no year] November 5 (Box 7)
      Paper watermarked 1855
    - 12 autograph letters, signed, to Henry Edward Bird. Brantwood., 1884-1888, undated (Box 7)
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, and one autograph letter with signature cut away to Mrs. Hugh Blackburn. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., [1881?] (Box 7)
      Accompanied by typescripts of the letters
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Blackburn. Coniston, Lancashire., 1885 April 23 (Box 7)
      Bought from John Heise Autograph Shop on the Plain Fund, 1941 March
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Lady Blaye de Bury. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1886 April 1 (Box 7)
      Bought from Pierre Beres on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2003 April 9
    - 6 autograph letters, signed, to Caroline Bowles., 1887 November 25-1888 June 8, undated (Box 7)
      Includes envelope addressed to Ruskin by Francesca [Alexander], with manuscript notes by Ruskin on verso; and 2 sheets of Ruskin's writing paper, with his doodles.
      Bought from John Wilson on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 2001 October 10
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, to George P. Boyce. Vevay, Lucerne., 1854 June 14 and 28, [1855] March 23 (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to C. Boyle. Denmark Hill., 1856 January 21 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997 October 20
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Reverand Stephen Bridge. No place., [no year] November 12 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2004 August 16
    - 5 autograph letters, signed, to George B. Brightling. Verne Hill, Denmark Hill, Oxford, Paris, Venice., 1872, undated (Box 7)
      Gift of Mrs. Gilbert M. Troxell [Library Associates], 1935 December 19
    - Autograph letter, signed, to "Brilleworth". No place., undated (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997 September 23
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Edward Brown. [Malven?], [no year] July 17 (Box 7)
      Gift of Philip Neufeld, 1988 October 11
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Burke. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1879 July 6 (Box 7)
      Bought from C. A. Stonehill on the Childs Fund
    - Autograph letter (signed by Anderson, Ruskin's secretary), and letter in Anderson's hand, signed, to Francis H. Butler. Coniston., 1884 September 15 and undated (Box 7)
      Includes 4 envelopes.
    - Autograph letter, signed with initials, to Mr. Butler. Brantwood., 1886 March 10 (Box 7)
      Bought from Catherine Barnes on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Cains. Denmark Hill., 1861 March 2 (Box 7)
      Bought from Maggs Brothers Ltd. with the Library Associates Fund, 1950
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Frederick Chapman. Brantwood., 1882 January 19 (Box 7)
      Bought from Henry Bristow on the Philip and Margaret Neufeld Fund of the Yale Library Associates, 1995 February 25
    - Autograph letter, signed, to R. Chester. Denmark Hill., undated (Box 7)
      Bought from John Wilson on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2000 September 30
    - 9 autograph letters, signed, to Reverand Edward Clayton. Various places., 1841-1849 (Box 7)
      Includes 1 envelope. 7 of the letters are incomplete.
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1996 December 12
    - 4 autograph letters, signed, to William Conway., 1886 March 23-1886 November 5 (Box 7)
      Bought from Jarndyce on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1981 April 1
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Ebenezer] Cooke. London., undated (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Cooke. Woodstock., undated (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1996 November 6
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Cooke., 1864 May (postmark) (Box 7)
      Bought on the Childs Fund, 1958
    - Autograph letter, signed, to F. Crawley. No place., (before 1876) (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Creswick. Coniston., 1877 October 31 (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Eneas Sweetland Dallas. London., [no year] October 23 (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Charles Dibdin. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1883 July 14 (Box 34 (Oversize))
      Mounted with an image of John Ruskin in his library.
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2005 June 2
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Reverand M. H. Dickinson. Denmark Hill., 1855 January 6 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Edward Dowden. Denmark Hill., 1871 December 4 (Box 7)
      Gift of Henry C. Hutchins, 1955
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Conrad Dressler. Heren Hill., 1884 March 6-7 (Box 7)
      Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, from Arthur Severn to Mrs. Myles Kennedy. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire. 1924 June 27.
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999 October 25
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Charles Grove Edwards. Denmark Hill., 1870 November 12 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2003 October 16
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Frederick Ellis. Rome., 1874 June 3 (Box 7)
      Includes clipping from catalogue.
      Gift of Henry C. Hutchins, 1960
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Edith Evans. No place., 1883 June 8 (Box 7)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999 August 25
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Juliana Horatia Gatty] Ewing. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., [1880] July 8 (Box 7)
      Bought from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the Library Associates Fund, 1950
    - Autograph letter to Richard [Fall] in verse. Paris., 1835 June 14 (Box 8)
      General note
      Mounted on stubs. Edges are charred, affecting the text.
      Gift of Charles E. Goodspeed, 1942
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. F. M. Faulkner. Denmark Hill., 1866 September 8 (Box 8)
      Accompanied by typescript.
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert, 1958
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Fawkes. Brantwood., 1883 June 10 (Box 8)
      Accompanied by a pamphlet, "Brantwood in the Twentieth Century" by J. S. Dearden, 1975 January 20; and a flyer, "Ruskin Lived Here".
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Edwin W. Field. Denmark Hill., 1869 February 15 (Box 8)
      Bought from Kenneth Rendell on the Charles J. Rosenbloom Fund, 1973 June 25
      Accompanied by photocopies of the letter
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Joseph] Fisher. Lancashire., 1880 July 17 (Box 8)
      Bought from Black on the John Ewing Durand Memorial Fund, 1960 March 7
    - 19 autograph letters, signed; 12 autograph letters, signed with initials; 1 autograph postcard; 1 autograph letter with signature cut off; and 1 letter written by an amanuensis to Albert Fleming. Oxford, Lancashire, and various other places., 1873-1888, undated (Box 8)
      Gift of Henry C. Hutchins, 1952
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Banister?] Fletcher. Brantwood., 1884 July 23 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Clare Ford. Denmark Hill., [no year] October 22 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Douglas W. Freshfield. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1878 August 27 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998 July 29
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Douglas W. Freshfield. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1878 September 1 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to P[eter le] N[eve] Foster. No place., [1856] March 27 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Reverand R. W. Galbraith. Penrith., 1857 September 24 (Box 8)
      Bought from John Wilson on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998 September 1
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Gaskell. No place., 1856 March 17 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2000 September 19
    - Autograph letter (incomplete) to Mrs. Gaskell. Oxford., [1857 July] (Box 8)
      Gift of Mary A. Benjamin, 1953 July 3
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mrs. Gaskell. Bolton Bridge., [1859?] March 9 (Box 8)
      Bought from Michael Silverman on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1990 May 8
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Margaret Emily] Gaskell. No place., undated (Box 8)
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1950
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Girdlestone. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., [1880] (Box 8)
    - 38 autograph letters, signed, to Albert Goodwin. Various places., 1880-1886, undated (Box 8)
      Includes 17 envelopes, and typescripts of all letters.
      Bought on the Library Associates Fund, 1952
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 1 autograph letter, signed with initials, to Mrs. Alice (Desborough) Goodwin. Brantwood, Coniston, and London., 1873 March 13, [1873 November 3], 1886 April 23 (Box 8)
      Includes 2 envelopes.
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, to W[illiam] Buchan Graham. Oxford, Ramsey, Knaresborough., 1875 October 16, November 24, [no year] May 15 (Box 8)
      Includes 3 envelopes.
    - Autograph letter, signed, to W. B. Graham. Grantham., 1876 April 25 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1997 April 17
    - Autograph letter, signed, to W. B. Graham. Knaresborough., 1876 April 30 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1997 April 17
    - 15 autograph letters, signed, to William Graham. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire, Venice., 1876-1886 (Box 8)
      Includes 13 envelopes.
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2001 August 8
    - Autograph letter, signed, to W. B. Graham. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., [no year] May 5 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Griffith. No place., [1864?] (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Cha[rle]s B. Grimaldi. Brantwood, Coniston., 1883 June 23 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to James Hall. Denmark Hill., [1848] March 11 (Box 8)
      Gift of Walter L. Pforzheimer, 1970 December 8
    - 2 autograph letters, signed, to S. C. Hall. Lancashire., 1872 May 27 and May 30 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mary Florence Hamilton. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1889 August 4 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1998 November 23
    - Autograph letter, signed, to George Harley. Coniston, Lancashire., 1887 June 15 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Harris. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1885 March 25 (Box 8)
      Bought from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 1997 April 9
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Thomas Hay. Denmark Hill., 1869 February 24 (Box 8)
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert, 1958 March 7
    - Autograph letter, signed, to [Frances] Hay. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1880 May 9 (Box 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Mr. Haydon. Herne Hill., 1875 February 14 (Box 8)
      Bought from Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1999 March 30
    - Autograph letter, signed, to Miss Hays. Brantwood, Coniston, Lancashire., 1880 March 9 (Box 8)